Hello everyone, welcome to this video.
In this video we will be discussing
about Azure AI search.
Azure AI search, it's a search engine.
We all know what does the search engine
do.
So, you will have enterprise data, you
pass the data to the search engine,
search engine will create an index, and
then like using the search method you
can retrieve the data and use it in your
application. Azure AI search provides
the traditional search experience
where like you can do a filter, scoring,
you know, synonyms or whatever is that.
And on top of that it also provides AI
based retrieval. Say like you have a,
you know, embedding, using the hybrid,
you can use the
keyword based search as well as the
embedding search, combine it together.
And then you can send the top results to
the LLM and generate the final result
instead of just having the chunks. So,
before we move forward, we will try to
understand the difference between
the traditional keyword based search and
the advanced embedding based search. So,
let me navigate to this particular
portal. Let me search for the keyword
"Zat eye ear". So, basically like I'm
looking for a eye drop.
However, like if you see here this
particular
e-commerce portal does not have this
particular product. As it uses the
keyword based search, it is not
returning any values because like there
is nothing they have it with the given
name.
But if you see that if if they don't
have this particular product, they
should identify that this is the eye
drop and then like they should display
all the relevant eye drops. So, now let
me navigate to the another portal here.
If you see this particular portal, I
just say like the same keyword. However,
like even this e-commerce portal they do
not have the
products. However, like
they recognize that this is the eye drop
and then like they showcase all the
alternative.
So, if you see here, this e-commerce
portal uses the advanced search, where
in this particular portal uses the
keyword search. So, the main difference
is that keyword search will look for the
given keyword. Wherein like the
uh embedding or the you know rag based
search
will not only look for the keyword, but
then like it will also look for the
synonyms.
Now, with that understanding, let's go
to this uh documentation and try to
understand. Now, we will try to
understand the pipeline here. If you see
here, firstly we will have a data
source. Sometimes uh it may be a storage
account, sometimes it may be a SQL
Server, Cosmos DB, or anything
for that matter, right? And then like we
will have a indexer. Indexer it's a
Think of this way, it's a scheduled
automation. So, that will go to the data
source and read all the you know latest
and greatest information,
and it will create an index.
So, indexer will be using skill set. For
instance, like let's say like you have a
video file or audio or a PDF file or a
Word document. So, the indexer should be
able to extract the data out of all of
these. So, for each of these content,
you will be using a specific skill set.
Say like there will be a one skill set
that will let you read the image. There
will be another uh skill set that will
you know convert the data into the
embedding uh embedding data, right? So,
the indexer will be using n number of
skill set uh to create the index, and
then like finally it will commit that uh
data into the index table.
Now, let's also talk about the uh types
of search.
I already mentioned that there is a
keyword search or a simple search. And
then like we also have a vector search.
I showed you like what is the difference
between all of these.
And then like there is also a third
category called a hybrid search. So,
hybrid search basically it does both the
keyword search, the embedding search,
and then like it combines the uh result
to produce the final result.
And then like we also have a hybrid plus
semantic ranker. So, if you if you think
of this way like
you know, it's kind of Lego pieces, so
you can stack them you know, on top of
each other.
So, first we will have a keyword search
and vector search. Both are you know,
sits at the same level. And then like
hybrid search, if you think like there
is going to be a Lego that connects both
of the keyword search and the vector
search. And then like on top of that
hybrid search, we have this semantic
ranker.
So, the semantic ranker will take the
result from the hybrid search and then
like it will apply its own formula to
optimize the search result.
The order of the search results will be
optimized using the semantic ranker.
Then finally, all of these are uses the
algorithms. A simple uh search, vector,
hybrid, and then like semantic ranker.
All of these uses algorithms. And the
fifth one that we are going to talk
about, it's the knowledge base. This is
not necessarily the algorithm, but
rather like this is a pattern.
So, until this point in time like what
we will be sending back to the caller,
it's kind of a chunk, right? So, in this
case like in the knowledge base, what it
will do is that it will take the chunk
out of this semantic
semantic search. And then like it will
use the LLM to convert that chunk into
the final result. So, that the end
application will not be receiving the
chunk, rather like it will be receiving
the processed final result.
So, if at all you wanted to showcase,
you know, top three, five results, then
you will be using
these you know, any of these
search type, keyword, vector, hybrid,
semantic, any of these. Whenever you
wanted to showcase here like you you
were searching for this particular item.
So in this case I say like we are you
know looking for this
Z editor product. And then like
there is there is no final result here
rather like we were wanted to showcase
the relevant product, right? So in this
case like it makes sense to use you know
any of these
types. Most likely it will be the hybrid
plus semantic search.
But then like in in case of a you know
chat application, you don't want to have
end number of result rather like you
wanted to have the final result. So at
that point in time you wanted to use the
knowledge bases. So again, the knowledge
base it's not necessarily the algorithm
rather like it is all built on top of
the semantic
ranker you that uses the LLM to you know
process the received number of result to
produce the final outcome. Now let's
assume that we have the uh movie
database and see like how does the
search
types will produce the search results.
So let's say like you're looking for a
keyword called Cyborg.
Uh which technically means that you're
looking for a robot kind of a thing.
Uh but then like with the keyword
search, it will exactly look for the
exact keyword Cyborg. It will look for
the exact keyword and wherever it
matches, it just returns those
film name.
But uh with the uh vector search, it
will not only look for the keyword but
rather like it will look for the
semantic match. In this case, it will
match
the robot uh you know you know uh
machine and all those things and it will
produce the result. And hybrid search,
it will take both the keyword search and
the vector search and it will combine
that
to produce the final outcome. And then
like finally we have this uh semantic
ranker. What it will do is that it will
take the hybrid output and then like
apply the
semantic on top of the hybrid result.
So, basically like
it will think that hey, like the user is
looking for this keyword, what exactly
will
satisfy the user? All right, so from the
user context it will
you know, reorder the result.
Now, as you realize that the search
results are getting better and better
from keyword to vector to hybrid to
semantic, the cost and time both will
increase.
So, now let's do the comparison here.
So, if you see here the cost pyramid,
the simplest one or the cheapest one is
the keyword search and then like when
you go up to the leader, the cost will
keep on increasing because you will be
doing multiple process.
Same thing for the time pyramid also, if
you see here the simple one, it's at the
bottom and then like when you go level
above, the time will get increased too.
So, you have to consider both at the
cost and time when you think about the
search type that you wanted to use. It
would be our strategy to select the
search model here.
So, this is the assumption that we are
using for this our calculation. So, if
you see here like we are talking about
100 GB of data in index size and then
like data refresh it's like 10% of that
which is like 10 GB.
And then we will be using the standard
tier
capacity. We will cover like 40 capacity
and monthly traffic like we are looking
at 1 million queries every month and we
will be using the small vector based
dimension here.
And we are talking about the regular
documents without any images, without
you know, a lot of OCR needed. And this
pricing it's as per May 2026. Now, with
that assumption let's compare all four
search model here. First we will start
with the keyword search. Cost efficiency
it's excellent.
So, again, like you need to understand
that
uh these search model, it's kind of a
Lego pieces are stacked on top of each
other.
Which means that there is no one set of
pricing. There will be a foundational
pricing, but the like as you add the
features, each feature will add you the
cost.
So, the keyword search will cost you
about 600 to 750.
And the like a use case, let's assume
that you you are a specialty store. Say
like you will sell flower or you sell
auto part. In that sense, all you need
it's the deterministic filters. Let's
say somebody will come and look for the
sunflower or jasmine or whatever is
that, right? So, these standard
keywords, you can very well use it in
your use case. Then you can use the
keyword-based search.
And when you're
you know, comparing the hybrid one, it's
like a combination of keyword plus
vector.
And the like the cost will be about 700
to 950.
And the like the use case will be
e-commerce. I already showed you like
what is the difference between the
keyword and I know hybrid search.
Now, let's also talk about hybrid with
semantic ranker. The cost will be about
1,700 to 2,000.
This will be at enterprise level. It
will not be available for the public
usage because like the cost it's a
little bit high.
Right? So, say like your employee wanted
to look for a legal, you know,
complaints details or a policy details,
then you can very well use the semantic
ranker.
And the final one it's the
knowledge base.
So, basically it's a rag-based system.
So, the cost will be
3,600 to 13,000 dollars.
This is more mostly used for a chatbot
kind of application. Right?
So, now let's move forward.
Now, let's try to understand the pricing
tiers here.
So, before we talk about that, we need
to understand the search unit. So,
basically like let's say let's say like
you are creating an index.
So, the index will be your replica. So,
in order to do a highly high
availability, you will be having a
number of replicas.
Within that replica, you will be having
a number of partition.
So, say like your index size it's you
know 100 MB. Uh sorry, 100 GB. Then now
you don't want to keep it in a single
partition, rather like you wanted to
have a multiple partition.
Um why we want to do that? If you just
come over here,
based on the uh skew that you select, um
the size storage size that it falls. So,
you cannot exit. Say like I wanted to
I'm I'm I'm using S1 stand- standard
tier.
And the storage uh that max I can go
it's a 25 GB.
So, say like you have a 40 GB, then you
cannot have it in a single partition.
So, you have to create multiple
partition.
So, if you see here, uh replica it's uh
your full index and the like within that
full index, you will have a number of
partition.
Uh based on the skew that you're using.
Not only that, uh there is other
reasons, too. So, if you if you see
here, this is a search unit. It's the
combination of uh replica and the
partition. Say here like I have three
replicas, two partition, the search
units will be six.
And the like when to use uh this uh
scaling like we can very well increase
the replicas as well as the partition.
If you just come over here, we can very
well increase the replicas as well as
the partition. But, when do we do that?
So, say like you you have multiple users
like concurrent number of concurrent
users are keep on increasing, then you
wanted to have a multiple replicas so
that you're not everyone will be hitting
the same index.
Um but the like there will be a number
of copies, so they can you know go into
multiple nodes to get the result. Under
like the storage it's hitting your limit
and then you have to do a partition. And
this is where like this
skew comes into picture. So, if you just
come over here if you if you already see
here, so there are multiple offerings.
There is a free offering. So, you know,
if you're an individual and you want to
to understand the search capability then
you can use the free tier. But the like
basic tier it's for, you know, dev test
and the like a standard tier for the
enterprise grade. Within standard tier
like we have a S1, S2, S3. You see the
differences here like in terms of a
storage there is a difference, right?
Not only in that like number of indexes
in indexes everything changes.
Especially the storage how changes.
So, based on your needs you have to
choose
you know, either of these. And the other
option it's the storage optimized say
like you have a huge amount of data that
you want to put it into your search then
you will be using the storage optimized.
The cost will be totally depends on the
offering that you select. So, if you do
a simple calculation here the basic
search will be like about $75 and the
like the standard search will be $250.
And the like the storage optimized will
be $3,000 close to $3,000. Again like
this is this is just a you know, very
foundational price. It is not everything
like you have to add up everything to to
come up with a some
you know, calculated numbers. If I just
come over here you will we already
discussed that, right? So, the basic
search one the
skew itself it's not going to cost you
much but the like the additional things
that you add on top of that it's what
going to cost you the additional
money.
Now, is the Azure AI search expensive?
Of course it is expensive. But the
reason is that there are n number of
features that you can select, right? So,
depends on your needs you will be
choosing the features. For instance,
here I listed the top 10 features. So,
the keyword search, vector search,
hybrid search, semantic ranker,
multi-model search, and you know,
embedding all of these, right? So, when
you add each of these, then it is going
to introduce the additional cost. So,
not necessarily the Azure AI search
itself it's expensive, but because like
you opted to select the features that
will add the additional cost. So, do we
have any alternative for Azure AI
search? Of course, like we do have a lot
of alternatives.
So, depends on the need, you can choose
the alternative. For instance, a
PostgreSQL.
You have to understand that you when you
buy the Azure AI search, you're buying a
product. But when you're using the
alternative, it is not necessarily will
give you all the feature, rather like it
will give you a portion of that. And
then like you have to do the
configuration or do the additional
development. So, the additional
development will also come into the
picture that is going to add you the
cost. In general, like if you think that
you will be using at least the five
features
provided by Azure AI search, then I
would say like just go with Azure AI
search. Okay, so far we discussed a lot
about the various type of search and the
like of skills, use cases. Now, let's
try to implement that. So, before we do
that, let's try to understand the skill
set. I already told you that the indexer
will be using the skill set to perform a
specific action. So, if you see here
like this is how we can define the skill
set. If you see here like I'm creating a
a split skill. So, basically like what
it will do is that it is going to
split the pages. Say like you're
uploading a PDF file 100 pages. You
don't want to put everything into the
same chunk, rather like you wanted to
split the PDF into chunks, right? So,
that is why that is why like we will be
using the split skill. And if you see
here like maximum length, it's a two
2,000 and the like overlap will be
500 characters. And the like we will be
creating the
chunk out of that.
And the like the other same way like we
can also create the embedding skills.
So, that is going to take the you know
split content and convert that content
into the embedding.
And we can also use the entity
organization. So, you extract some data
from the data you wanted to extract the
person, you know, organization, or any
other information
or entity that you wanted to extract,
you can will extract.
And the like when we talk about the
pipeline, I already showed you like how
does the pipeline works. So, you will
have an indexer. Indexer it's a
scheduled indexer. It can be scheduled,
it it can be manual. So, indexer will
will, you know, talk to the data source
and it will extract the data and the
indexer will use the skill. It can use
multiple skills. Firstly, it can use the
split skill to split the document and
the like it can use embedding skill to
convert the
split data into the vector. And the like
finally, it will create the index and
commit the index so that the committed
data, the index will be available for
our consumption. So, now let's talk
about the chunking here.
So, let's say like I have a piece. So,
10 pages page, right? So, I don't want
to
save complete page into the vector. So,
usually like I we will be splitting that
into a number of pieces.
If you see here page one, page two, page
10, whatever is that, right? So, we will
split everything and the like create a
chunk of for that particular page.
And when we say like
we wanted to create a vector, like how
do we create a vector, right? So,
typically like we will be using
the uh embedding models or to create the
vector. So, you have to remember that
you are using a specific uh embedding
model to create your
uh vector. And when you do a search, you
have to use the same model to create the
vector uh so that you will get the
results back.
So, if you see here like there are two
different models available for us. Like
there are a plenty of available, but
then like these two are from uh GPT.
So, the small model and the large model.
The small model will be having 1,536
uh dimensions, where like the large
model will be having
uh 3,072 dimensions. The accuracy will
be uh 62.3%.
This accuracy will be 64.6%.
So, basically like when you wanted to
have the uh precise uh search results,
then you you need to use the large
model. But the cost will be very
expensive. So, if you see here,
this is uh 0.2
uh cents, where like this is 13 cents.
So, it's extremely high.
So, now let's move forward. Now, this
one explains how does these uh embedding
works. Now that we understood
everything, let's go ahead and uh set up
the search here.
So, first we will create the uh keyword
search. We'll have the data source uh
using the indexer. It will create a
index. Let's go to the Visual Studio
code. So, if I just come over here,
the way we implemented, it's like first
we create a data source.
Uh let me go here. So, it just creates
the data source here.
Uh once the data source is created, then
we will we can create a index.
So, basically index it's just a table,
right? And then like we will finally we
will have our indexer.
So, the indexer will populate the index
uh
And finally we can do a search here. So,
if I just come come to the search here.
So,
what I want to search, it's like the
cyborg kids what I want to search and I
wanted to print the results here. So, I
already executed here and if you see the
result, it is just giving me these two
because like it is explicitly mentioned
here in the search
in the description.
Uh here you you see cyborg and here also
you see cyborg.
That's how we implement the keyword
search and for the vector search, it is
almost similar except that if you just
come over here, we will create a data
source, we will create a index and then
like we will create a skill set. If you
just go to the
uh skill set, we are just uh using the
uh embedding skill set. So, instead of
just uh the keyword, we will be using
the embedding here.
And then like finally we will click uh
call the indexer to populate the index
and finally we will do the search here.
Exactly the same thing but this time
around uh we will be using the uh vector
search.
Right? So, we are using the vector query
and uh we we get the result. So, if I
just come over here,
so this time around if you see here, it
is returning uh slightly a different
result here. So, it is uh you know,
giving me the Terminator, I, Robot and
Terminator. Well, let's talk about the
hybrid search. Hybrid search uh in terms
of implementation is going to be the
same but if you just come to the search
side, what you will do is that uh here
where like uh you will be seeing the uh
high both uh you will be setting here.
Right? The search text as well as the
uh vector queries, both you will be
passing. If you just come to the uh
vector search, you will be just passing
the query
uh vector query but uh hybrid search,
you will be passing search text at the
vector query. Both you will be passing.
That is the only difference in terms of
uh implementation.
And the result, it is going to be almost
identical to the uh vector result here.
Now, let's also implement the hybrid uh
semantic search. It will be exactly the
same uh similar to the hybrid search
except that if you go to the index,
we will also have the semantic uh search
configuration here.
So, if you see here like uh this is the
semantic search configuration where like
we say like uh focus on these uh fields.
Uh remember like this database has a
number of field out of that like these
are all the field that we wanted to
focus on for the semantic search
configuration. So, give a lot of uh
priority to this uh field title field.
And then like uh you focus on this uh
film synopsis. Uh basically like uh
whatever the content field that we
configured here,
the LLM will read uh as a paragraph and
try to identify the uh information out
of this particular paragraph. And this
field uh it's what we wanted to focus on
for the keyword search.
So, now uh the results will be almost
identical. Uh maybe like the order will
be slightly adjusted. Now, we can go
back to the Azure portal and see all of
this.
So, if you see here like I have the SQL
database. So, this database it's what I
will be using for the search.
And if you see here like uh I using the
uh pricing tier basic
under uh replica one, partition one,
search unit one.
And then like uh from here only we can
do the import. Uh like whatever we have
done through the code that can also be
done from the portal. So, if you click
on this import, that will let you uh
choose the target. So, in this case this
is going to be SQL server. And then like
what kind of search you want to do. Here
like you can choose the database that
you are interested in and the table that
you are interested in. You can choose
all of these and then like you can
choose the authentication mechanism. I'm
not going to do that, but you can very
well do that here.
Uh and also you can also add a index and
search the uh existing index. So, now if
I just come over here, this is where
like you will see all the uh data source
that we added through the code. So, this
one for the keyword search, vector
search, hybrid search, and semantic
search. So, all of these are added and
we are focusing on the uh table frame.
And the like uh for some of these we
have created the skill set. Uh you can
find all the skill set here. So, the
thing is that uh you can also create uh
everything from here. Um it's a JSON
format. You can very well do that here.
So, let me open the uh vector definition
skill set here.
Uh so, this is how you create. So, just
give it a name, give it some
description. You can see like the
deployment ID and the like a dimension
model name, input and output. And this
is how you can create the skill set.
Once the skill set it's created, then
you can create the uh index.
So, you can very well create the index
here, too. So, let me open one of the
existing index. So, if you just come
over here,
uh field it's what uh we wanted to
define. So, if you see here like uh we
we have defined, I know, so many fields
you know, corresponding to the database
table that we have. And uh whether we
wanted to retrieve, this can be used for
uh filter, sortable, uh face table,
searchable, whatever it is that we can
we can choose all of these here.
And the like uh if you have the semantic
configuration, this is where you will
see or you can add it here. Vector
profile also like if you have one, that
will be displayed or you can add it
here.
Uh so, now let open one of these uh
uh maybe like the semantic one I open.
So, if you just come over here, the
field wise it will be the same field
except that we will be adding one
additional field to store the vector
information here.
And then like if you just come to the
semantic configuration, exactly the same
thing, right? So, the priority field it
is going to be this and the content will
be in this and the keyword search will
be using this
field. And the vector profile, you can
see it here.
So, this is how we create the index and
then like finally we will create an
indexer. When you create an indexer, it
is going like you can create the indexer
from here.
Or open the existing index. Let me open
the semantic indexer here. So, if you
see here like it is going to when you
create the index, you can edit the index
too.
These are all the information that you
wanted to have to create the index, uh
sorry, indexer. And then like you can
run the indexer from here.
So, it can be scheduled index or it
can be a manual run also.
So, now if I just come to the indexes,
now let me pick up you know any one of
these, maybe the keyword search. And if
you do the search here, maybe like I'm
looking for the keyword
cyborg.
So, it is going to give me the result
here. We can also work on the scaling.
So, if you just come to the scaling,
here well like you can configure your
number of replicas, you know,
partitions, and you can also choose the
various uh
uh pricing tier.
Uh and then like if you just come over
here, from here you can get the keys.
And uh if you come over to the premium
features, you can choose the premium
features. So, if you see here like right
now I'm using the free feature. So, when
like
uh 1,000 semantic ranker per month, it's
free.
Uh but then like if you go with the
standard one, then uh the price will be
added.
Right? This is how we can use the Azure
AI search. Thank you for watching.